Guide to the Edith Segal Papers TAM.684
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edith Segal Papers
1918-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Segal, Edith, 1902-
Segel, Shari
TAM.684
3.96 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 2 folders in shared housing, and audio-visual materials in shared box
1 audiocassette
2 sound tape reels
1 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
Edith Segal (1906-1997) was an American dancer, teacher, songwriter, and poet. Throughout her life Segal was a committed leftist, and her work was closely tied to her political activism. The Edith Segal Papers (1918-1999) chronicle Segal's life as a teacher, dancer, poet, and political activist. Materials from the original donation in 2016 relate generally to labor activism and life in early-20th century America. They include materials collected by Segal, including a scrapbook from World War I; printed matter on topics including New York labor laws and May Day; and photographs of Labor Day rallies. The 2023 accretion consists of materials on Segal herself, and her participation in the civil rights and leftist movements. Her commitment to these causes can be viewed in her correspondence with prominent civil rights activists and the subjects of her many poems and New Year's cards, which include Ethel and Julius Rosenberg and Angela Davis.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Shari Segel in 2015; additional materials were donated in 2018 and 2023. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2016.005, 2018.089, and 2023.016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Items in the first series have been retained in their original groupings and arranged in roughly chronological order. Items in the second series also have been retained in their orginial groupings, with loose items interfiled accordingly; files were further arranged in chronological order within groupings.
Biographical Note
Edith Segal (1906-1997) was an American dancer, teacher, songwriter, and poet. She was born in New York's Lower East Side in 1906 to working-class Jewish immigrants. Throughout her life Segal was a committed leftist and civil rights advocate, and her work was closely tied to her political and civil activism. A supporter of the Soviet Union, Segal formed the dance company the Red Dancers in 1929 and choreographed performances in honor of V.I. Lenin. Her other works focused on topics related to civil and workers' rights as well as Jewish cultural themes. She created her most famous work Black and White in 1930, which was the first interracial dance performance in the United States.
In addition to dancing with her company, Segal taught at several leftist camps and recreational resorts in New York and New England, including Camp Kinderland, the Unity House, Cedar Isle Camp, Camp Nitgedaiget, and Camp Wocolona. In the mid to late 1930s, she was also involved with the Works Progress Administration's (WPA) Federal Theatre Project in New York and Detroit. Segal wrote several books of poetry, including three for children, from the 1950s to the 1980s, some of which were illustrated by her husband, Samuel Kamen. Throughout her career, she also wrote and lectured on dance.
Segal remained active in the arts and political communities up until her death in 1997 in New York City.
Related Archival Materials
Edith Segal Papers, call number: (S) *MGZMD 122, Jerome Robbins Dance Division, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, Dorothy and Lewis B. Cullman Center, 40 Lincoln Center Plaza, New York, NY 10023-7498
Scope and Contents
The Edith Segal Papers (1918-1999) chronicle Segal's life as a teacher, dancer, poet, and political activist. Materials from the original donation in 2016 relate generally to labor activism and life in early-20th century America. They include materials collected by Segal, including a scrapbook from World War I; printed matter on topics including New York labor laws and May Day; and photographs of Labor Day rallies. Additionally, there are items created by Segal, including drafts of skits, one of which is about a workers' strike. The 2023 accretion consists of materials on Segal herself, and her participation in the civil rights and leftist movements. Her commitment to these causes can be viewed in her correspondence with prominent civil rights activists and the subjects of her many poems and New Year's cards, which include Ethel and Julius Rosenberg and Angela Davis. Her passion for performing and teaching dance is reflected in performance programs, flyers, sound recordings (audiocassette and audio reels) and photographs. There is a small amount of personal material, including a family tree, awards, honors, and tributes. Segal was beloved for her teaching and activism, which can be gleaned from the fan mail that she collected over the years.
Separated Materials
Issues of the publications Workers' Theatre,1931-1933 (call number PN2000 .N49 Non-circulating); New Theatre, 1933-1937 ( call number PN2000 .N49 Oversize Non-circulating); and one issue of Photo-History, July 1937 (call number AP2 .P5585 Oversize Non-circulating) have been transferred to the library collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Appraisal
One flash drive was deaccessioned because it contained duplicate photographs.
Agitprop theater; Dance for children; Labor movement -- Political activity -- United States.; Lyricists; Radical theater; Scrapbooks.; Women choreographers.; Women dancers.; Women poets, American.; Women singers; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects -- United States.; Segel, Shari
- Series I. Original Donation, 1918-1985; .23 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a small assortment of items created and collected by Segal. These materials relate generally to labor activism and life in early-20th century America. They include a scrapbook from World War I; a pamphlet on New York Child Labor and Compulsory Education Laws (1918); flyers from a May Day Rally and a skit satirizing the Civilian Conservation Corps in the 1930s; an article from Home and Education (1941), a magazine for Jewish mothers and teachers; and a report from the United Workers Cooperative Colony 50th Anniversary (1977). The collection also includes four photographs of Labor Day rallies in Detroit (circa 1937-1938), and a folder containing reproductions of photographs taken by Lewis W. Hine for the National Child Labor Committee.
  The collection contains German-language ephemera from the Prolet Buehne in New York City, and two of drafts written by Segal, which include a 1937 script for the skit "Million Dollar Baby," about a strike at the Woolworth's department store, and "I Remember Rose: A Remembrance of Rose Pastor Stokes" (circa 1980s).
  - WWI Scrapbook, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyers -- Performance and Rally, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs -- Labor Marches in Detroit, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Million Dollar Baby" by Edith Segal (Skit on the Woolworth's Strike), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "For Our Child, Our Future" in Home and Education, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - United Workers Cooperative Colony 50th Anniversary, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "I Remember Rose: A Remembrance of Rose Pastor Stokes" by Edith Segal, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lewis Hine Reproductions, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to and from Yalta Children, 1966-04 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box Shared Tamiment 037)
    Includes a recorded phonodisc.
  - Theater Ephemera, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photo History: Labor's Challenge, 1937-07 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Accretions, 1930-1999; 3.73 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes and 1 1/2 manuscript box; 1 audiocassette; 2 sound tape reels; 1 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
  The 2023 accretion consists of materials on Segal herself, and her participation in the civil rights and leftist movements. The correspondence files reflect her commitment to these causes; prominent correspondents include well-known civil rights activists Ruby Dee and Ossie Davis, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Pete Seeger. Additionally, there are a number of letters to and from the Soviet Union. Most of these letters refer to Segal's poetry and its message of peace. Segal's career as a poet can be gleaned from the vast amount of drafts, New Year's cards (with illustrations by her husband, Samuel Kamen), and published poems and songs in the collection. Performance programs and flyers showcase Segal's career as a dancer, and photographs, slides, and audio reels of performances at Camp Kinderland reflect Segal's career as a dance teacher. Fan mail, which includes various letters and poems from schoolchildren and a vinyl record from children from Yalta, and various awards and tributes, also reflect her contributions to the fields of dance and poetry.
  - Family Tree, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Honors, 1967-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tributes, 1956-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Allen, Charles R., Jr., 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Asner, Ed, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Baez, Joan, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- Bates, Daisy, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Belafonte, Harry, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Bitter, Albert, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence -- Board of Education of the City of New York, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence -- Bomzer, Heidi, 1953-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- Bunche, Ralph, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence -- Burrows, Vinie, circa 1965-1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence -- Childress, Alice, 1971-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence -- Chile, Public Figures, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence -- Cronbach, Abraham, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Dassin, Jules, 1972-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence -- Davis, Angela, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence -- Dee, Ruby and Ossie Davis, 1963-1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence -- Du Bois, Shirley Graham, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence -- Dupuy, Jacques, 1953-1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence -- Eisman, Harry, 1959-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence -- Farkas, Alex, 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence -- Fast, Howard, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence -- Fireman, Hy, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence -- Foreign, 1961-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence -- Gellert, Larry, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence -- Gibson, Larry, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence -- Giovanni, Nikki, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- Girl Scouts of America, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Golden, Harry, 1959-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Goodman, Carolyn, 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Graham, Hugh, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- Graham, Martha, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Grant, Charity, Joseph, and Sharlane, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Gross, Chaim, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence -- Guthrie, Woody, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence -- Hughes, Langston, 1945-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- International Publishers, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence -- Jara, Joan, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence -- Johnson, Oakley, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence -- Kahn, Albert E., 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence -- Kennedy, Jacqueline, circa 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Kent, Rockwell, 1955-1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence -- King, Coretta Scott, 1969-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence -- King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence -- Le Sueur, Meridel, 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence -- Letelier, Isabel, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence -- Lehrman, Leonard, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence -- Library of Performing Arts, New York Public Library, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence -- Lieberman, Ben, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence -- Lowenfels, Walter, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence -- Lüdecke, Heinz, 1931-1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence -- Maltz, Albert, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence -- Merriam, Eve, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence -- Mobilization for Youth, 1965-1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence -- Morford, Richard, 1961-1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence -- Murphy, George, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence -- Naponach Prison, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence -- Neeley, Lyn, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence -- Nemiroff, Robert, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence -- North, Joseph, 1958-1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence -- O'Casey, Sean, 1957-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence -- Patterson, William and Louise, 1967-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- Picasso, Pablo, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Pomeroy, Bill and Celia, 1962-1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Randolph, John, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Refregier, Anton, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- Robinson, Jackie, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- Rosenthal, Irwin, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Rosten, Norman, circa 1945-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence -- Schwartz, A. V., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence -- Seeger, Pete, 1948-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- Senators and Members of Congress, 1975-1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence -- Shappes, Morris, 1966-1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence -- Siqueiros, Angélica Arenal de, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence -- Somerville, John, 1977-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence -- Soviet Union, 1956-1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- Spiegel, Marcia, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence -- Spock, Benjamin, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence -- Sporn, Paul, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence -- Suhl, Yuri, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence -- Thomas, Norman, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence -- UNICEF, 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence -- Unitarian Church and Union Hall (Ann Arbor, Michigan), 1938-03-14 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- Uphaus, Willard, 1960-1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence -- Weigl, Vally, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence -- Winestone, Will, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1937-1959 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- General, 1980-1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Fan Mail, 1954-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1, Sound disc--vinyl 684_0004)
  - Correspondence -- Fan Mail, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence -- Fan Mail, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Fan Mail, 1972-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Address Lists, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Performance Programs and Flyers, 1942-1988 (Box 6, Folder 6, Box 7, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 162, Folder 14)
  - Performances, 1959-1968 (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Quarter inch audio reel 684_0002-0003)
  - Publishers and Permissions -- Correspondence, 1949-1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Quotes of Support for Publications, 1964-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Publicity, 1953-1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Published Work -- Poems, Songs, and Essays, 1937-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5-7, Box Shared Tamiment 084, Audiocassette 684_0001)
  - Published Poems -- Rosenbergs, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Published Poems -- Moscow News and Russian Books, 1960-1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Poems and Songs for Camp Kinderland, 1960-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, circa 1940-1949 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, circa 1950-1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, circa 1960-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, circa 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, 1980-1984 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, 1985-1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Drafts of Published and Unpublished Work, circa 1990-1999 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Poems Translated into Spanish, Yiddish, and French, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Rejected Poems, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - New Year's Card and Song Lists, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - New Year's Cards, 1952-1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - New Year's Cards, 1966-1980 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - New Year's Cards, 1981-1999 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and Negatives -- Camp Kinderland, circa 1939-1999 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Photographs and Negatives -- Trip to Cuba, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Photographs and Negatives -- Tribute to Edith Segal, New York University, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Photographs and Negatives -- General, circa 1930-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Slides -- Camp Kinderland, 1960-1970 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Slides -- Mosholu-Montefiore Center Dance Class, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Slides -- National Guardian Picnic with Pete Seeger, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Slides -- General, 1956-1978 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Materials, 1961-1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)